Guide to the Lindley Williams Hubbell Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Lindley Williams Hubbell papers,
1934-1999.
Hubbell, Lindley Williams, 1901-
3.09 linear feet (5 document boxes and one record storage box).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
MS#0627
4078938
The collection contains the correspondence and written works (both published and unpublished) of the poet and ex-patriot, Lindley Williams Hubbell.
Biographical Note
Lindley Williams Hubbell, poet, translator, and expatriate, was born to a well-to-do family in Hartford, Connecticut on the 3rd of June, 1901.
Hubbell's formal education was brief. He dropped out of Hartford High School after two years and was subsequently educated by private tutors in Greek, Latin and Provencal. Having an affinity for languages, Hubbell later learned German, French, and Italian from a polyglot aunt.
Hubbell spent the bulk of his American career, from 1925-1946, as a reference librarian at the New York Public Library. He would rely on his skills in library sciences later in his life, during his initial time living in Japan.
Hubbell received a Yale Younger Poets award in 1927, and his books of poetry were published by major publishers in the US. He was an early admirer of Gertrude Stein; he corresponded with her and wrote an article defending her first early novels. He was a regular companion of Stein's during her 1934 trip to New York City.
Though Hubbell never went to university, from 1946-1953 he was the Head of the Literature Department at Randall School in Hartford, Connecticut, where he taught the history of drama, Shakespeare, Ibsen and Modern Poetry.
In 1953, after the death of a cousin and the consequent inheritance he received, Hubbell moved to Japan and began to work as a cataloger at the library in Daitokuji Temple. This would lead to his professorship at Doshisha University and later to his becoming a Japanese citizen (1960). Once he had taken Japanese citizenship, Hubbell never again left Japan and officially changed his name to the Japanese, Shuseki Hayashi.
Hubbell was an admirer of Nô drama and saw 186 out of the extant 240 plays, 849 performances in all. He helped translate Kadensho (secret teachings on Nô performance) by Zeami (1363 - 1443), published by the foundation of Sumiya-Shinobe Scholoarship (1968). He also dedicated himself to Shinto, especially to the beauty of its ceremonies and rituals, its music and dance.
In 1970 Hubbell, along with his friends and fellow scholars Hisao Kanaseki and Yoko Danno, established a non-profit, private press known as the Ikuta Press. Through this Hubbell published 16 volumes of his own poetry and prose.
Hubbell retired from Doshisha in 1970 and went on to teach at Mukogawa Women's University in Nishinomiya until the age of 86. He continued to write throughout his later life. Lindley Williams Hubbell passed away in 1994 in the Kunishima Hospital in Kyoto.
A memorial stone was installed by his former students, friends and colleagues in the precincts of Kannon-ji Temple in Oh-yamazaki, Kyoto.
Scope and Content
The collection consists predominantly of correspondence from Lindley Williams Hubbell and compiled by friends. There are also early passports of Hubbell's, his official expatriation documents, business cards, drafts of creative works, and several published books and pamphlets written by Lindley Williams Hubbell.
This collection is arranged in 3 series
Series I: Correspondence, 1934-1999
Series II: Biographical Documents, 1961 and undated
Series III: Writings and Publications, 1933-1983
Subjects
Hubbell, Lindley Williams, 1868-1960; Hubbell, Lindley Williams, 1901-; Shakespeare, William--1564-1616--Criticism and interpretation.; Shakespeare, William--1564-1616--Authorship.; Haiku.; Poets.; Poetry--Japan.; Theater--Japan.; Theater--Elizabethan.; Theater--England.; Japanese poetry.; Japanese literature.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
Robert Wilbur Gift in memory of Roland O. Baughman, 1968. Gift from Hiroaki and Nancy Sato to Columbia University in 1998; gift from Yoko Dano to Columbia University in 1999; gift from the International House of Japan to Columbia University in 2002; gift from David Burleigh to Columbia University in 2010.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1934-1994
  - Hubbell to Yoko Danno, 1966-1993, (5 Folders) (Box 1)
  - Hubbell to Barbara Hart Davitt, 1953-1985 (Box 2)
    (includes poetry and written works)
  - Hubbell to Maurice and Blanche Jaffer (Box 2)
  - Hubbell to Hisao Kanseki, 1934-1972, (6 Folders) (Box 2)
  - Hubbell to Donald Richie, 1937-1983, (4 Folders) (Box 2)
    (includes letters, postcards, poems, and writings sent from Hubbell to Richie)
  - Hubbell to Hiro and Nancy Sato, 1943-1963, (5 Folders) (Box 3)
  - Hubbell to Michiko and Paul Snowden, 1974-1977 (Box 3)
  - Hubbell to Stephanie Samek Terenzio, 1956-1994 (Box 3)
  - Hubbell to Martha Osborn Vinick (Box 3)
    (Contains a number of poems)
  - Hubbell to Various Correspondents, 1960s-1998 (Box 3)
- Series II: Biographical Documents, 1961 and undated
  - Biographical Notes and Bibliographies (Box 4)
  - Business Cards (Box 4)
  - Passports (Box 4)
  - Expatriation Documents, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Clippings and Memorabilia, (2 Folders) (Box 4)
  - Poetry and Cards (Box 4)
- Series III: Writings and Publications, 1933-2005
  - Manuscripts
    - "Atlantic Triptych," undated (Box 4)
    - Essay on No Drama, undated (Box 4)
    - "The Mountains," 1951 (Box 4)
    - "Ninety Questions about Plants" poems by Hubbell, Yoko Danno, Hiroko Fujioka, and Hisao Kanasaki (Box 4)
    - "Origins of Art: A Lecture," 1945 (Box 4)
    - "Phaedra," 1945 (Box 4)
    - Various Drafts and Manuscripts, 1933-1983 (Box 4)
  - Printed Material-- Offprints and Publications
    - American Poet-- 6th Issue, 1941 September (Box 5)
    - Cicada vol.2, no.2, 1978 (Box 5)
      (contains Hubbell's "Linked Poem")
    - The East-West Review vol. 1, no. 1, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Frogpond Magazine vol. iv, no. 1, 1981 (Box 5)
      (includes haiku by Hubbell)
    - "Gertrude Stein: The First Period" offprint, 1980 (Box 5)
    - "The English Hexameter, 1976 (Box 5)
    - "Modern Poetry"-- lecture, 1983 (Box 5)
    - Mukogawa Literary Review offprints issues 17-21, issues 210 and 21, 1982-1985 (Box 5)
    - Oedipus at Colonus, 1978 (Box 5)
      (translated by Hubbell)
    - Poems-- Haiku by Zenrin Kushu, Calligraphy by Oda Sesso (Box 5)
    - Poetry Nippon Magazine no. 59, 1982 (Box 5)
      (contains "Ennui" and "Mar Gabriel")
    - "The Prosody of Mauberley," 1982 (Box 5)
    - Sixteen American Poets, 1976 (Box 5)
    - "Spenser's Epithalamion," 1971 (Box 5)
    - The Supplicants, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Theatre World Magazine, 1940 June, October and December, 1941 April, June and 1949 November, (2 Folders) (Box 5)
    - Translations, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Published Books
    - The Tracing of a Portal, 1931 (Box 6)
    - Winter-burning, 1938 (Box 6)
    - Long Island Triptych, 1947 (Box 6)
    - The Ninth Continent: [a poem in ten parts], 1947 (Box 6)
    - Seventy Poems, 1976 (Box 6)
    - Ze-ami Kadensho, by Miyai, B., Sakurai, C., Hayashi, S., Hubbell, L. W., & Satoi, R, 1968 (Box 6)
    - A Note on the Shakespeare Apocrypha, 1966 (Box 6)
    - Trilogy, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Atlantic Triptych: Lindley Williams Hubbell, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Dark Pavilion, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Miscellany, 1972 (Box 6)
    - Double Triptych, 1974 (Box 6)
    - A Second Miscellany, 1975 (Box 6)
    - Pasiphae, 1976 (Box 6)
    - Autobiography, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Climbing to Monfumo, 1977 (Box 6)
    - Trilogy, 1977 (Box 6)
    - The Ten Avatars of Vishnu: A Cento, 1978 (Box 6)
    - Walking Through Namba, 1978 (Box 6)
    - The English Lyric in the Eighteenth Century, 1979 (Box 6)
    - Czerny, 1981 (Box 6)
    - The English Lyric in the Seventeenth Century, 1981 (Box 6)
    - The First Architect, 1982 (Box 6)
    - Studies in English Literature, 1982 (Box 6)
    - A Geography of the United States, 1999 (Box 6)
    - George Borrow, 1960 (Box 6)
    - Shakespeare and Classic Drama, 1960 (Box 6)
    - Lectures on Shakespeare, 1972 (Box 6)
    - The Works of Lindley Williams Hubbell-- CD-ROM, 2005 (Box 6)